<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>/^blog$/</title><link href="http://vsjha.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://vsjha.in/feeds/python.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://vsjha.in/</id><updated>2015-01-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>A Blog Using Pelican !</title><link href="http://vsjha.in/a-blog-using-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Vivek Jha</name></author><id>tag:vsjha.in,2015-01-26:a-blog-using-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="" src="images/pelican.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a long time I was looking for a blogging solution which is not just
hassle free to manage but also cheap and easy to host. At the same time I
was is no mood to trade the configurability aspect for the above features.
And also I didn't want to learn any new technology just for the sake of
maintiaing a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I explored several options, and went through many articles which had monotonous
titles like &amp;quot;5 best blogging framework ....&amp;quot;. Out of all this exercise two obvious
choices stood out, viz. &lt;strong&gt;Wordpress&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Blogger&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though they are very good solutions for the problem but somehow it did't match my taste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-wordpress"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Wordpress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond doubt this is the most popular blogging framework and probably
the most feature rich also. But the main reason behind it's popularity is the
strong community and the rich admin console which can be used to control
most of the aspects of the site from the admin console. And this was the big reason
for wide adoption of Wordpress becuase you really don't need to be techie to
own a blog. Please with limited computer knowledge were able to manage and host
their own blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hunted down this option because of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too many features which I actually didn't need. I wanted to keep it just as simple as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configuring it would require me to learn PHP, which doesn't find a place in my technical roadmap. (at least after learning python!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hosting requires more money than I was ready to spend. (I told you it has to be super cheap)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Theaming also requires to understand the Worpress jargon which is overwhelming for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="blogger"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Blogger&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also a nice framework and I used it for quite a while for running a
puzzle blog. It was far simpler than &lt;em&gt;wordpress&lt;/em&gt; which I consider a plus but
it was somewhat boring as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you see blogger in last 5 years, nothing much has changed, this is very
unlike all other Google products. Looks at it only feels that Google is using
it as just one more medium to push their advertisements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very few templates to choose from and look and feel of all of them reminds to
the web of 2005 era. Most of the widgets are only there for sake of increasing
the number of widgets, very few are useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="static-site-generators"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Static Site Generators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new concept really excited me when I heard about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://Jekyllrb.com"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; through Github.
It was really somethig which I was looking for. I can write articles on
any plain text editor, which was a great plus. And there were many templates to
chose from. Being static site it only had features which a static site can afford
to have without an active application server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there was a problem. It's not really a Jekyl issue, but rather a personal
taste. I did't know Ruby and for making any changes of higher order would require
some Ruby knowledge. Though it's a nice language to learn (unlike PHP) but my
priorities were not allowing me to go into that direction. I was just wondering
whether is there anything like &lt;em&gt;PyJekyl&lt;/em&gt; !!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="and-finally-the-pelican"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And Finally the Pelican&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of python is, you name it and you have it. And a static site
generator was no exception either. It only took few google searches to
reach &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://docs.pelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;. And it had almost everything which I wanted. It hardly
took anytime to impress me to a point of no return. At a glance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Had almost all essential features which a blog should have. (and did't have ones which I consider overkill)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Templating was super easy because of Jinja2 templating system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could write in &lt;em&gt;rst&lt;/em&gt; format. I am more fluent in &lt;em&gt;rst&lt;/em&gt; compared to &lt;em&gt;markdown&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don't have to write in a WYSIWYG editor, comfort of &lt;em&gt;vim&lt;/em&gt; was there to stay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration with almost all the cloud service out of box.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next was the theme hunt. I always wanted to do it myself rather than using a readymade (mostly for learning sake).
But I found an amazing theme which I could use as a great starting point. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/DandyDev/pelican-bootstrap3"&gt;Pelican-Bootstrap3&lt;/a&gt; is an
amazing project. It is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://getbootstrap.com"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; based theme (one more tech which I am comfortable with) and does
just enough to make a great starting point. That doesn't mean it is not directly usable, in fact it looks
pretty descent. It supports most of the Social stuff and cloud services. To name a few:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Analytics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disqus for comment handling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AddThis - For adding social buttons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="github-pelican-a-killer-combo"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Github + Pelican a Killer Combo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using Github to host the blog which you are reading right now. It's a
very easy to use it you work with git (All of us do). And you dont have to
pay anthing for this. It is free !! All you need to pay if for domain and
that too is not mandatory as long as you are happy with the gihub sub-domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="python"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="blogging"></category></entry></feed>